foreign
so my first question
was actually
you spoke about it in the last video
by as it happens it was related to
what you mean by
delighting in sensuality
and but you did speak it about it in the
last video and it was quite
um
clear when you said that it's kind of in
that attitude of anticipation initial
attitude of anticipation or background
attitude of anticipation towards a
particular experience or something
um
and then I think the question that I
wanted to
just to make sure that just to clarify
it is
what would be the difference between
the lighting in a sensual a thought of
sensual nature
and like engaging mentally
like engaging mentally
in a
in sensuality is there a difference
between those two things um
um
well yes but not like they're not on the
same level so if if you were not
delighting you wouldn't be able to
engage mentally yes so Delight is the
basis for mental engagement so you can
then not engage mentally but still
Delight yeah but if you don't Delight
even thinking about the sense of objects
it's not centrality because there's no
Delight the writing okay that's
good that's kind of what I thought that
the Delight is more like the yeah the
necessary condition for you to be able
to engage in a thought of sensual nature
in a sense that to welcome it Enlighten
it
except but you know the joy the promises
and so on like basically to take it for
granted and so then even like you know
even if you're just sitting and not even
moving or doing anything
there is a difference between having
like an attitude of wanting to go
towards something welcoming it and
delighting it and then you can then even
actively think then there is this active
thinking about
about something of
whatever pleasant experience that you
want to have or something that you can
like actively be thinking about it but
before that there has to be already or
prior let's say you're kind of
underlying if there is that attitude
yeah which remains there gives you gives
the meaning gives the context of what
what your mind is revolving around and
uh and that's why that was a lot of
people good more often than not meditate
with sensuality
I mean to say the same and the point is
exactly that so you may not be you might
be saying no to the um Central object so
you're not engaging with them you're
refusing to think about them you're
concentrating away from them you're
getting rid of those thoughts but ease
your mind still expecting pleasure
Delight in joyful
ideas of whatever meditation experience
uh and so on and it's like yeah so
that's that is your intention that is
your that is your intention that is your
that is your intention that is your
context that is your motivation
um
so like when you sit to meditate to easy
to meditate on account like um in a way
of
Discerning the enduring body there the
base is what is subjected to all these
Reflections or do you see to meditate to
constantly to evoke to get to produce
the experience of of pleasing kind and
then that's just exactly the same
Central principle
okay yeah
yeah um
um
that's in that sense like giving people
you know will take on the seal and The
Virtue but in that kind of a conditional
way they will take it because yes they
were told they need to take it in order
to get this special experience of
meditation or Enlightenment but if
you're actually if your meditations on
the level of reviewing your situation
the body the context the danger the
battle the disenchantment that it's
better to give it up then you realize oh
no CLI virtue is what protects me from
falling deeper into this
it's self-conditional anymore it's
indirectly for what it is abstaining
from certain Act is what created this
context of recognizing the Trap debate
and everything else yeah
that brings me to another yeah that's
that's exactly the other thing I wanted
to
um
ask about or check
is that this um
this um
it seems that the danger
in relation to
sensuality or
but again another come back to that in a
minute but
or even a whole the whole domain of the
senses and engagement into the sense is
involvement with the senses
um
they
because there's let's say two broadly
speaking aspects of danger that kind of
appeared more or less clearly to me in
at different times
one of which is really in relation to
the nature of this particular type of
let's say
you kind of you can learn to recognize a
particular type of let's say perception
or if if you're in seclusion there's
nothing else it's more like a thought
type of toss
that is
um it's not about you know initially it
will be about certain types of objects
but it's more about the nature of the
thought that it's like it contains an
invitation or a hook or a it requires
you to it wants you to do something to
um
become involved in a particular type of
sense of object or particular type of
activity or experience in some way and
it's like
but then in relation to that
there is the danger
of like
the Mind becoming Disturbed and you
having to kind of hang yourself you're
becoming involved hang yourself on this
particular object or
I'm not to put it like that
um that you become dependent on all of
this this experience getting something
wanting something what will happen if I
don't get it what will happen on account
of this becoming busy on account of it
um um and
um and
and yeah so that's the kind of type of
of danger of see the danger of
involvement or being required to do a
particular thing is there a more even
more immediate type of danger implicit
that's this there is it seems like a
second aspect of danger which is really
um
more about the fact that the foreign
foreign
about the nature of the body as such or
the senses as such
um
but that nature is there regardless of
whether you're engaging with neutrality
or not so what's dangerous about it
in one case and why it isn't dangerous
in another case yes
because
the reason why
yeah because if um
if you can kind of let's say
you see you start to recognize that
regardless where does the pain come from
suffering what's the origin of suffering
the craving the craving yeah and what is
the where does that craving exist
is it a physical thing no it's in your
attitude towards so it's a mental it's a
mental thing
is it mental craving because any craving
is mental so is the craving uh a method
of choice
can you choose to play or choose not to
pray so craving is something the Mind does
so craving is something the Mind does
which means suffering is something that
mind causes
uh is the Mind something you ask for
something you can control something you
can um on something that obeys you no kind
um on something that obeys you no kind
of
you're aligned with it so to speak it
obeys you most of the time if the
circumstances are all right but if
circumstances change
that's when you realize you know that
man doesn't actually want to listen to
you you can't stop it
and then you suffer encounter it
so then
you want to be free from suffering means
you need to be free from craving which
means you need to teach your mind how to
stop doing it all you need to basically
understand your mind or surmount your
mind either way mind does the craving
so how do you then stop that
and that's where the danger is
that's where the danger is
the dangerous in reality
is the danger of still the slide doesn't
matter the little bit of sensuality
means there is still a little
possibility of that mind craving against
you against itself resisting patiga against
against itself resisting patiga against
anything that that and you can't control
that so you cannot you can have wishful
so you cannot you can have wishful
thinking and hope that the mind won't
because you know you're so calm and
you've been keeping precepts for so long
fundamentally for as long as there is a
trace of sensuality the other back side
of that same Trace same phenomena same
values of sensuality is the value of the
wild mind which means the craving
remains there
and if you want to see whether your mind
still has that
uncontrollable threat they would turn
against itself and cause you immense
suffering if if circumstances change if
you lose Health life and so on uh yeah
just practice sense restraint and
Solitude and you'll see when the mind
doesn't get what he wants it's going to
start getting wound up
and then you will recognize that that's
the root of the suffering it's the
craving so I can't stop the craving I
can't will it away I can't I can't just
choose it but what I can do is tame the
mind so it becomes unable to turn
against itself
and and that's where you recognize the
true dangerous in reality so giving in
to Central desire even on the mental
level valuing it means allowing mind to
remain mild to that extent and sooner or
later that will bite you back so it's
not a what I'm trying to say it's not a
delayed danger it's the other side of
the same coin
okay that's that when danger becomes
apparent means this
um as we said this anticipation this
delight literally this thing while it is present
literally this thing while it is present
the background of it is mind eating
itself the possibility of it won't do it
there but the fact is you're allowing it
and if you go that way to that extent
you gave your own mind room to turn
against itself and then it will sooner
or later it will as long as you don't
abandon that attitude and there's
anticipation and you don't see it
thoroughly the the Peril of giving into
that direction once you do and as they
would have said you dry up from
centrality internally then the mind the
animal will be completely tamed it will
forget how to turn against itself
and that's where you recognize that okay
so now suffering cannot arise
even if the circumstances are completely
falling apart around me everything
disintegrating what cannot happen is
mind turn against itself
because you tamed it but you won't aim
it for as long as there is as long as
you allow it to eat debate or welcome
debate or Delight in debate
so think about it babe
and the base we refer to is basically
the prospect of pleasure sure
your pleasure Delight in pleasure
prospector pleasure
um so debate is also like it's not
Prosper to pleasure can show a debate
but I also uh simply kind of not seeing
the danger enough
that's also what the bet is
that's what it means is that not
recognizing Dubai
seeing the danger
is how you basically stop valuing the
pleasure and raccoon has debate the
beta's debate yeah the bait is debate so
it's not well I'm trying to say it's not
like that you need to actively seek out
and then oh I don't actually seek out
thus I'm free from bait no do you now by
okay you don't actively seek out but do
you not see the danger if you were to
see God and if you don't see the danger
to that extent yeah
you don't see the bait it's not super
danger yeah exactly and when debate
when this Prospect is seen as debate as
something that will hook me then the
last um decreases well no when the prospect
um decreases well no when the prospect
of that
anticipation is seeing this thing is
what makes mine bite itself exactly
that's what I meant yeah that's when you
can do not there's nothing no pleasure
in the world if you want to accept it
because it's not the it's that like
there's nothing to do with the thing
nothing no it's it's that like giving
into that or maintaining that or not
seeing the danger of that
and perpetuates
um enables the mind and perpetuates that
enabling of mind to bite itself when
things change
when you pay what you don't want
separated from what you want the you
know the five codes of central pleasures
and so on you and you know that you know
that you you will not be able to stop it
you can just hope and ignore it but
factually if there is a room for a mind
to bite itself it will because you
allowed it and that's the danger so yes
you can involve the future parallel and
dissatisfaction sure to Reign it in but
fundamentally accepting this means
mind-biting itself
yeah that's that's exactly what I what I
meant like that that's that's so nice to
um
matches um
yeah like the the danger is in that
any kind of
um
that's what you just said so I don't
need to repeat it but like that that's
the day that's that is the danger it's
nothing to do with like what will happen
in the future what could happen in the
future or whatever because yeah that's
like oh you could it could not happen or
it could be fine whatever like but it's
it's just that fact of
being hooked one of like having this
um
yeah having a hook having a push having
a
having any kind of craving is in itself
to be not desired to be not welcomed
because it's the way it's like the Gateway
it's the way it's like the Gateway
toward to Hell really yeah it's yeah
um yeah there's great mass of suffering
as the person describe yeah that's it
that's because of that the great muscle
suffering and the great mass of
suffering is always uncomfortable the
same same yeah that is everything else
is second to it and as we described
presence of craving craving full stop is
something that the mind that has a
maintained will do our case with
agreeable disagreeable or neutral
which means the great mass of suffering
remains something that you're under so
you are liable to it you will be
subjected to it but if the the danger of
sensuality has been understood I.E oh
okay so without if I stop if I don't
give into this if I don't welcome this
because now I see if I do this is the
result the result is mind remaining able
to eat itself if it wants to in a Split
Second not like you know we're gonna be a long
not like you know we're gonna be a long
process all you need to do is face with
something you don't want to face with
and all the dread and pain and
everything will be instantaneously there
because the mind will just try to turn
away from it to resist it because again
you let it you're like you you gave it
room to do so so and that's why it's
it's it's hard to see because you know
room to do so doesn't mean the mind is
doing it all the time so you then forget
that the mind can still do it it can
still turn against itself
can still want to deny its own existence
out of pain and aversion and hatred and
ill will and so on
but because it's not doing that all the
time you sort of forget that there is
room for it to still turn around and
sink it stiff okay so that's the danger
yeah and that was something
um that was another Point that's that's why
that's why
like it's not
um
being like having a kind of a sense of
safety or something
is not about
um just currently not feeling any sort
of pressure of the central kind because
you can have that even like for quite a
long time for example sure
um but as soon as something comes up
something arises there's some then if at
that moment then you will be like going
in that direction not able to
see the problem in it not recognizing it
for what it is then there is no safety
really at all so it's it's the but so
what is the safety then the true safety
and the safety is when you know where
the danger is then you know that no
matter when it will so you know now that
the danger is in mind being able to turn
against itself so what is then the
safety um well if you see the danger of that
um well if you see the danger of that
then
the if the mind is able to turn itself
if the mind is able to turn itself
against itself what makes the mind being
able to turn itself against itself
that's something that you are
responsible for that you can choose to
not do so if you recognize the danger of
doing that which makes the Mind able to
turn against itself then you can not do
that yeah and then eventually the mind
will cease to be able to turn against
itself yeah
craving cannot arise
yeah so you said that now like
recognizing where the danger is
is the necessary condition for
um safety
um
and then is there but is there yes there
also a sense that the kind of
um
I think it's something slightly
different
like let's say from the perspective of
um
not being not having any safety
there's if you're if you're still like in the
if you're if you're still like in the
domain of of sensuality and kind of uh
involved in it
I kind of don't see how it's possible in
a way to see the danger in it it kind of
requires at least say
maybe not the complete sense of safety
but at least a pretty complete seclusion
from that sort of domain in order to
then have the perspective sensory
strength in gardening with the sense
those is a free requisite that's
normally optional yeah it needs to be
your lifestyle your model being yeah of
course in itself you will still not see
where the danger is and so on but for
sure if you if you're not withdrawn then
you remove even possibility of seeing it
it's like we said before like lighting
the fire so they would say you know the
sticks are in the water wet you take
them out of the water first
like if you try to light the fire with
the with sticks in the water that's just
not going to work so you take them out
but they're still wet so although yes
they're out of water
they're still wet so they're still
online the fire but now at least there's
a possibility than drying if you don't
put them back in the water and once
they're dry thoroughly then you can
light the fire
and that's it the mind is first
physically withdrawal from sensuality
through through and behavior you
withdraw it by not giving into this
Behavior because you recognize on it no
a car Faith to a degree but at the same
time you do recognize I've been going
down the direction of the senses my
whole life and uh look I want to
practice I want to be free from
suffering because this is what it
resulted in
so then you found that Buddhist teaching
you have a degree of Faith you start
applying it and you can't even
intellectually make sense that actually
it's better if I'm out of the water even
if I don't necessarily see the immediate
imminent danger the direct insight into
freedom from sensuality and so on well
at least I have possibilities to do so
if I stay out of the water yeah
and like that but in and of itself that's
like that but in and of itself that's
not a goal yeah yeah exactly the goal is
to like fight and you don't forget that
yeah um
and again just to clarify slightly
further that being out of the water
because this could maybe be understood
in different ways
um
as far as I can see it really has to
become quite a complete
seclusion as in it wouldn't really be
because yeah you can be kind of more or
less restrained in keeping the virtue but if
restrained in keeping the virtue but if
you are still like busy
um doing various things and kind of
distracting yourself in any way really
then you kind of can't really even see
this the the which type of
yeah well that's like you know seeing
the danger in the slide his fault does
not mean seeing the danger in the
slightest fault of the latter and the
the the semantics of the rule
the semantics of the rule
means the danger of the slightest fault
in terms of okay so yes I'm not breaking
this I'm not giving it to Desire by body
but to this course extent but am I still
to this course extent but am I still
looking forward to anything things that
are allowable as we said before yeah
yeah you must stop eating with that
desire you can't stop eating that's the
point but if a person never recognizes that's
but if a person never recognizes that's
where the true danger and and fault is
and still remain on the level of you
know oh I studied all the dictionary and
I got the definition of the rule and
this is what objectively means and and
our fault of that in regard to that
interpretation is what I didn't even
fall so I just need to fix the
circumstances and make everybody else so
bad that's not seeing the fault that's
not allowing basically vinaya and sense
restraint to make you practice on the
level of the mind that is just using it
to protect yourself
through that magical belief that that's
where the Purity is
so in order to abandon still about the
Paramus you need to reference where the
fault is and it's not in the latter it's
not in the in the definition it's in
like why am I doing this so you'll find
something that's not against the rules
but that still doesn't absolve you from
needing to know and feel the weight of
why you're doing it yes coffee is
allowable to have in the afternoon
and I can have sugar but why why am I
doing this
where is distributed oh yeah it's been
you know it's been traditionally often
touched you know with the Bowing triple
bowing on a tray so it's just the purest
offering I can imagine in that external
form sense but yeah but that's that's
irrelevant the fault is not in how it was done and
the fault is not in how it was done and
presented the fault is why am I doing
this do I need it what forward is this rooted
do I need it what forward is this rooted
and then same would come to exactly like
oh yeah so you know we are allowed to to
work and do these things and like but if
a lot yeah what else like it's even yeah
these duties that you perceive are kind
of self-evident and objectively valid
that's not where their their validity is
determine it's determined by your
intentions and the reasons why you do it
so yes obvious things out of greed the
version delusion 8 presets basically
are not to be broken but now all the
other implementation doesn't mean you
can dismiss that
quite the opposite means you need to
take more of them just on the right
level less specifically but more because
you're taking responsibility for where
the actual fault is the mind of Desire
mind of aversion and mind of distraction
but if we judge what needs to be done on
the basis of authority of the texts
which is again the contriction terms
like you will always have your
interpretation of it there is no such
thing as objective meaning of the text
it's what it means to you and to us and
vast majority of people might agree upon
the meaning but every single one of them
is individually subjectively responsible
for the meaning
so the weight of the tradition the
authority and so on that's not that's
not where these things are
but if you never abandon that out of
fear of doubt and so on well you never
allow your mind to recognize where the
true fault is and thus approve it out of
fear and doubt
so that's where like you need to get out
of the water for the sake of drying the
sticks not for the sake of trying
underwater and then just you know
defining what the water was and how
you're dry and you know what you must
what you can what you cannot do
from the point of view of desire you
can't do anything
yeah you're not out of water don't
matter and it's if the light in the fire is
and it's if the light in the fire is
your goal if not you know if just living
in a spiritual community of the degrees
upon certain terms and interpretations
is your gold and fun but that's not what
we're talking about um
so just to come back to this the degree
of let's say
the degree of seclusion
um
and it's
I think in the cities it sometimes even
says like phys he uh goes into physical
seclusion and mental seclusion physical
or physical withdrawal and mental
mentally secluded
um
are mentally withdrawn and can you be
mentally withdrawn if you're not
physically no you cannot so there's the
physical sense of withdrawal but even
um
there it needs more than like physically
being secluded let's say in a secluded
environment or just being restrained
there's necessity for mental to be
mentally withdrawn from
um
even mentally engaging in unwholesome
things waited for which you need to be
able to already see how you were
mentally engaging with unwholesome
things in order to then be able to see
the danger in doing so in order to then
kind of have any kind of sense of safety
yes so in other words you need to
basically want to like the fire
want to like the fire
and in order to do so
you need to abandon
things external things avoidance of
responsibilities external authorities
external agreements as the measure of
your safety
Purity practice and defining what you
need to do you need to abandon your
perceived sense of Duty
so you need to abandon sir about parmas
basically that's used you know these
factors and all these are just random
things they serve purpose
you're fatter willingly by them because
they protect you from that which is very
displeasing the weight of responsibility the weight
the weight of responsibility the weight
of interpretation the way the choices
and so on so which you have a choice to
make you can remain sheltered
covering things up or if you want to
uncover it then you have to unshelter it
that to me like the true safety comes
from mine being unable to turn against
itself but in order to arrive there
you need to stop covering up the fact
that the mind can't turn against itself
oh but I'm fine you know I keep the
precepts in a pure and devotional and
stuff is like yeah but that's that's all
just conditional
sure that's nice in a worldly sense [Music]
[Music]
but then you need to start asking
yourself why why am I doing this if if I
took oh no I agree with this with this
Authority with this traditional
interpretation or whatever else the way
what we should do fine but you still
need to know why and take responsibility
for it it's never on them it's never on
others it's never on the as I said on
the on the external world even if you
say yeah I'll agree to what you already
agreed that still doesn't absorb me from
needing to know why am I doing that and
think for myself and take responsibility
for it
but often that's exactly why it's done
see I will go with majority
with the tradition with the established
ways so I don't have to think for myself
but you are thinking for yourself now
you're just lying to yourself about it
because how would you choose to go with
a tradition with the established voice
unless you thought about it and
obviously felt some safety of account of
it and gave into it and now you're just
saying oh no I just go over I do what
others say
you do need to take responsibility for
it and then it ceases to be on that
level and then you realize it's all it is all
and then you realize it's all it is all
interpreter eight precepts are
interpretation like yeah you know you can bend in this
like yeah you know you can bend in this
way Bend in that way sure but
fundamentally you realize okay you could
extrapolate the principle of create the
version delusion Central desire ill will
uh carelessness distraction that is what
needs to be restrained how we Define it
and can I touch this and if it's touch
can I do this and well you know if I
said it okay you can go into these
details if it's helpful but not for the
sake of deriving safety from the
definition that you read in a book or a
senior man told you but simply from
knowing more how to recognize the root
of the problem in your mind
so the degree diversion division doesn't
hide from you or that you don't feel
absorbed from it
so in order to recognize that there is
nothing I nothing at all I have to do or
nothing at all that I can do that can
well that will absolve me from taking
responsibility for whatever I choose to
do yeah basically furthermore on a more
immediate level it will be if you
abandon syllabusa it will be like oh I
don't need to do anything in order to be
safe and that's unsafe
so the relief of abandoning the fat is
its factorial it's not intellectual and
it's on the exactly in that level see it
is a burden having to Define having to
follow having to update having to comply
having to do having to perform
all of that is a factual burden you
don't see the burdening aspect because
you emphasize the Sheltering aspect once
you stop exercising that aspect you can
actually eventually if you go in the
right direction abandon the burden of it
is no no quite the opposite
if I don't engage that way I am I remain
safe I remain unexposed so in a way it's
on account of the Lost perspective
I don't understand like you said that
you
you pay more attention in the way to the
Sheltering aspect but not to how it
affects you right well I wouldn't say
it's an account of loss of perspective
because you never had the perspective
like you know like you start by not
having perspective so it's on account of
the lack of perspective
loss would imply you sort of had it and
then you lost it
but no you start already fettered
yeah and that's why
that's why
it's like the in a way that like still
about a Paramus or for example
kind of covers up that's what it does
it's what its purpose is really is to
make something appear comfortable or
feel comfortable that isn't comfortable
and it shouldn't be comfortable and as
in this
what do you mean because
because
the avoiding responsibility
for things through having things duties
and others depending on other things
it's kind of
makes this
yeah makes it makes it comfortable I see
what you mean here makes it doable but
actually nothing has changed on a
fundamental level you're not closer to
lighting the fire
uh so you shouldn't be comfortable
you should recognize that
there is still plenty of room for mine
to turn against itself in many different
ways but yeah you will feel absolved from
but yeah you will feel absolved from
needing to deal with it
because you know
abide under the
the collective responsibility of
majority that we all contributed and all
partake and I'm safe safety of the group
sent to the tribe
it's kind of gone off in a different
slightly different direction I wanted to
come back to the
um
if it's okay we're kind of going in
different directions but it's I wanted
to come back to the hindrances
um
because
another question I had like I was
because I I often I realized basically
that often I would
um
sometimes it's not that clear to me even
what um
um
exactly is meant by uh say sensual
thought or a like a Yeah because
sometimes um
I often I'm kind of I think of it in
terms of
um
not necessarily defined by particular
yeah particular objects or having even
something necessarily being agreeable in
a way what I realized it that sometimes
things that I was thinking of as like
um yeah sensuality
um
because it really pertains to like
engaging in a some kind of experience or
feeling like the need to do something
really um but it's not really it would kind of
um but it's not really it would kind of
come down to I realized oh that's more
like doubt or that's more like kind of
another one of the hindrances the same
kind of the same yeah
so they'll bond together so it can be on
the level of specific sites about this
touch or like the overall uh
agreeability of the of you know the
experience but he does always imply that that sense
but he does always imply that that sense
of pleasure which is considered safe
friendly agreeable to me that's when that's it
agreeable to me that's when that's it
perfect celebrity it starts by yeah not
having sexual intercourse uh while he
was talking to Max and not having sexual
interest with women they're not touching
them they're not allowing to be touched
they're not um talking to them they're
not listening to them talk they're not
looking at them they're not thinking
about them then not wishing about having
a Rivers
um
so it was the extension of the same
principle so okay I might have abandoned
any kind of physical Karma all these
Pleasures they would be binding me here
oh but I still hope that this I will
find somewhere else here so new here
where it will be nice and pleasant and
safe for me where Pleasures will be
accessible so in other words are you still valuing
so in other words are you still valuing
a situation external to your State of
Mind here and now um
like if same like whether it's
meditation or any other if you're
expecting this thing to come on the
level of just this external experience
that just happened internally now and
everything else it's the it's the same
principle yeah yeah
you know you can't
you cannot necessarily tell your mind to
immediately stop thinking about those
things but you can certainly not lose
perspective or learn how to not lose
perspective or account of having those
thoughts present
yeah and I think this and what would be
the perspective by the way let's say how
would you not use a perspective on a
spectrum of sexual intercourse with a
you know whoever attracted to
up to the level of wishing Heavenly
rebirth and safety of Heavens what is
the the how would you maintain
perspective put it at any part of that
Spectrum any thought whatever it is what
would maintain the perspective of the
entire thing of the entire domain
what would maintain the perspective of
the why would we cannot lose perspective
whether it's a course Canal Central
recognizing that danger of that exactly
it's the same danger yeah it's the same
dangerous it happens you know it's
better actually sure if you have desire
to attendance then having desire to come
a pleasure here now with your father was
with far worse consequences
unintended consequences but
fundamentally if you want to be free
from it all fundamentally if you don't
want to leave the slightest room for
your mind to turn against itself
even in 100 million years of time in the
future it's see the same thing and then there
it's see the same thing and then there
will be no long format yeah and then the
craving will truly be abandoned yeah
yeah and that yeah yeah
because it's the dangerous scene there
then it really doesn't matter at all
whether like there is no kind of even
asking oh but it's a little or it's big
or it's smaller whatever
domain in whatever shape whatever it's
not about it's like
and and the thing is as well that's what
we're describing the suit is you know we
talk about the Aggregates and how it's
endangering them similarly and we said
it doesn't matter whether it's uh past
future present big small personal
impersonal um foreign familiar uh nice
light have it doesn't matter the
property of it the danger is seen the
same not mine not to be welcome not to be
not mine not to be welcome not to be
delighted in
and see that long enough and the mind
will come down in other words the mind
will become unable to turn against still
God cannot be done anymore
and that's like the description of the
true Freedom the true safety it cannot
be uh reverted back like a stone split
into Leaf sort of dried up it cannot now
go back
so it has complete completely dry fire
has been it sticks will burn yeah there
are no more sticks to be wet
but then from from the perspective of
value pleasure not exactly what a safety is
pleasure not exactly what a safety is
seeing but that's exactly what is Cena
say basically what this leads what is
dangerous like the bait sure sure the
prospect of oh let me get this let me
have it that's my safety because I enjoy
the comfort of familiarity the
friendliness of The Taste the debate has
and as we said last time it's not it
does not start when I act in the actor
it starts when I already with the
lightness you're already you're already
not seeing it is dangerous that's where
they started exactly what the we have
why that's even the danger is in the
Delight in it yeah that's the
gratification that's dangerous on that
level it's all on that in that same
kernel it's the same phenomenon it's
just different aspects of it
is the same thing in a way yeah so yeah
like if you were to not act out of the
light long enough and get to descend the
background not ignore it you would see
that the background of it is the debate
the Delight is debate exactly the bait
is the danger that the light is the
danger exactly yeah yeah that's really
and all the future consequences it's all
because of this this is the framework
this is a necessary basis this will be
there if those consequences are able to
experience and and yeah and it's and like from the
and and yeah and it's and like from the
perspective of seeing that then like the
slightest you know Prospect of you know going
you know Prospect of you know going
towards that going in that direction is
very unpleasant actually or it would be
very unpleasant it's like it's almost
like you know you're out of prison and
sure and now you see like the prison
guard is going oh no come back in here I
have some very nice um I don't know cake
see but the fear will be on the level of
oh this crazy mind might forgetting go
back yeah yeah like you know you
wouldn't but if the mind is still not
tamed if it still has room to move
that's the danger yeah and that was the
simile of the there was it the charcoal
pit okay yeah man initially goes
willingly there and burns himself with
the Embers because he perceives it
Pleasant today he gets cured he doesn't
have a ninja and if somebody were to
pick him up and carry him there wouldn't
he kick and scream it would be
everywhere else except there yeah and
it's like yeah you and you really can
see like oh God
you know why would anybody want to like
actually go in that direction when but
you do that's what I kind of meant in a
way for that you do already need the
perspective yeah
like some kind of safety you can't have
that um kind of perspective from already
um kind of perspective from already
being in it and seeing that as the
safety yeah you want to have like you
know seeing a principle will be done on
different levels like different layers
you'll be peeling it more and more but
yeah it will be the same thing but up
until to the point you realize that if I
were to die this next second
will my mind have aversion towards that
will it try to sort of you know resist
it uh fight it deal with it avoid it
close its eyes look away if so or if I'm
not sure means there is still room for
it to move yeah
to bite itself so that cannot
should not be allowed if I want to be
truly free secured from bondage